

4225 Pendleton Dr. Apt. 7104 Bryan, TX, 77802, USA

🛘 🖟 (281)-825-9621 | 🗷 michellemjonika@gmail.com | 🎁 michellejonika@github.io | 🖸 michellejonika | 🛅 michellejonika | 💆 @michellejonika

Summary.

As a computational biologist, I enjoy the puzzle-like nature of coding genetics and genomics problems, specifically bringing this approach to the evolution of genomic content and sex chromosomes. Detail-oriented planning, project management, experimental design, and clear communication are important to my critical thinking and problem solving strategies for research. I am pursuing a Ph.D. in Genetics and Genomics at Texas A&M University with an expected graduation date of Spring 2023, and I am interested in career paths in industry intersecting genetics, genomics, data science, and molecular biology.

**Expertise** 

Genomics: SRA, Trimmomatic, bwa, samtools, bamtools, GATK, PLINK, BUSCO, rrBLUP, GEMMA

**Genetics:** Genome structure evolution, Sex chromosome evolution, Morphometrics, Genomic analysis, Genome assembly

**Molecular Biology:** Primer optimization, gDNA/DNA extraction, RNA extraction, PCR, qPCR, Gel visualization/imaging

**Programming:** R, Linux/Unix, Git, tidyverse, conda, SQL, Python, LaTeX, HTML/CSS

**Data Science:** Large dataset management (>20Gb), Bayesian statistics, Phylogenetics, Simulations, Data Visualization (ggplot2) **Soft Skills:** Project management, Public Speaking, Leadership, Multi-disciplinary Collaboration, Adaptive problem solving

## **Education**

## Ph.D. in Genetics and Genomics (Graduate Business Certificate)

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M UNIVERSITY | ADVISOR: HEATH BLACKMON

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

· Dissertation: The Rise and Fall of DNA Sequences Among Sequence Classes and Genomic Compartments

### **B.S. in Forensic and Investigative Science (Minor: Genetics)**

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M UNIVERSITY | ADVISOR: AARON M. TARONE

Aug. 2014 - May 2018

• Thesis: Genes as Markers of Sex for Forensic Entomology

# **Experience**

Bayer Crop Science St. Louis, Missouri

DATA SCIENCE INTERN | GENOMICS DISCOVERY AND APPLICATION TEAM

May 2021 - Aug. 2021

- Identifying historic data to test for epistasis and designing a follow-up experiment to test for epistasis
- Developing a statistical testing framework to identify interactions between introgressed loci
- Three-month, full-time position exposure in an industry setting
- · Establishing multi-disciplinary connections with teams with expertise in data science, genomics, and precision breeding

#### Ph.D. Research | Advisor: Dr. Heath Blackmon

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M INTERDISCIPLINARY PROGRAM IN GENETICS AND GENOMICS | TEXAS A&M DEPARTMENT OF BIOLOGY

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

- Developing an R package (Lo et al. 2019) to characterize microsatellite evolution and applying this package to characterize microsatellite evolution across 300 million years of insect evolution (Jonika et al. 2020)
- Elucidating the role of centromere type in insect chromosome evolution (Ruckman et al. 2020)
- Designing an automated genomic pipeline and TensorFlow based machine learning application to categorize genomic characteristics for 100s of mammalian species totaling 1000s of TB of genomic data

#### Post-baccalaureate Research Technician | Advisor: Dr. Aaron M. Tarone

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M DEPARTMENT OF ENTOMOLOGY

May 2018 - Aug. 2018

Fall 2020 - Spring 2021

- Completed additional experimentation and formal writing from undergraduate thesis project (Jonika et al. 2020)
- Applied new sex determination methodology and primer optimization to additional applications in forensic entomology (Pimsler et al. 2021) and stem cell research (In Prep)

# Teaching & Mentorship\_

# **Teaching Assistant** College Station, Texas

DEPARTMENT OF BIOLOGY | DEPARTMENT OF BIOCHEMISTRY

• Introduction to Genetics Laboratory | Fall 2020, Spring 2021

- Critical Writing in Biology | Spring 2019
- Guest Lecture Bioinformatics | Topic: Genetic Privacy | Oct. 2019

OCTOBER 21, 2021 MICHELLE JONIKA · RÉSUMÉ

Graduate Student Mentor College Station, Texas

Undergraduate Research Assistants Aug. 2018 - Current

- Mentee: Johnathan Lo | Topic: Microsatellite Characterization and Evolution
- Mentee: Abhi Arekere | Topic: Carnivore Chromosome Number Evolution
- Mentee: Ragan Miller, Joseph Ward, Leen Fardoun, Alexandra Constantinov | Topic: Chrysina Morphometrics
- Mentee: Grace Fischer | Topic: Tribolium Dispersal Patterns

# **Management & Outreach**

#### **Texas Genetics Society**

**BOARD MEMBER - STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE** 

Mar. 2020 - Current

Organize annual Texas Genetics Society meeting

### **Genetics Society of America**

EARLY CAREER LEADERSHIP PROGRAM - CAREER DEVELOPMENT SUBCOMMITTEE

Jan. 2020 - Current

- Contribute career development blog pieces for Genes to Genomes blog
- Curate resources contributing to a career development toolkit and early career researcher newsletters
- Organize career development workshops for bimonthly workshop series and TAGC conference

#### **Genetics Graduate Student Association**

PRESIDENT | VICE PRESIDENT | GRADUATE STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE | SEMINAR COMMITTEE

May 2019 - Current

- Facilitate monthly graduate student association meetings
- Oversee communication between current graduate students, genetics faculty, and the program executive committee
- · Represented the genetics interdisciplinary program in the graduate and professional student government

#### **Coding Workshop Facilitator and Instructor**

F: FACILITATOR | T: TAUGHT | \*: CO-TAUGHT

Apr. 2019 - Current

- Texas Genetics Society R Workshop, TGS F (150 attendees)
- R Hackday, Texas A&M Department of Biology T\* (50 attendees)
- R Workshop, Aggie Veterans Who Code F (15 attendees)

### **Texas A&M College of Science**

OUTREACH COMMITTEE | WOMEN IN SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Jan. 2019 - Current

- · Participated in various outreach activities important to the mission of the College of Science and Women in Science and Engineering
- · Served on the Women in Science and Engineering outreach committee and organized school STEM nights

### Awards & Grants

- 2021 Outstanding PhD Student Poster Presentation, Texas Genetics Society
- 2020 **Outstanding PhD Student Oral Presentation**, North America Forensic Entomology Association
- 2020 Genetics Graduate Student Oral Presentation Award, Interdisciplinary Genetics and Genomics Program
- 2019 **Texas Ecolab Fund Grant**, "Evolution of Sex Chromosomes in Tiger Beetle Species of the Southern U.S."
- 2019 **1st Place Genetics Science Art Competition**, Interdisciplinary Genetics and Genomics Program
- 2019 Genetics Graduate Student Association Travel Grant, Interdisciplinary Genetics and Genomics Program

# **Publications**

M.L. Pimsler, C.E. Hjelmen, **M.M. Jonika**, A. Sharma, S. Fu, M. Bala, S.H. Sze, J.K. Tomberlin, A.M. Tarone. 2021. Sexual Dimorphism in Growth Rate and Gene Expression Throughout Immature Development in Wild Type Chrysomya rufifacies (Diptera: Calliphoridae) Macquart. Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution. 9: 368.

S. Ruckman\*(Co-first author), M.M. Jonika\*(Co-first author), C. Casola, H. Blackmon. 2020. Chromosome Number Evolves at Equal Rates in Holocentric and Monocentric Clades. PLOS Genetics 16(10):e1009076.

M.M. Jonika, J. Lo, H. Blackmon. 2020. Mode and Tempo of Microsatellite Evolution across 300 Million Years of Insect Evolution. Genes 11:945.

M.M. Jonika, C.E. Hjelmen, A.M. Faris, A.S. McGuane A.M. Tarone. 2020. An Evaluation of Differentially Spliced Genes as Markers of Sex for Forensic Entomology. J. of Forensic Science 65(5): 1579-1587

J. Lo, M.M. Jonika, H. Blackmon. 2019. micRocounter: Microsatellite Characterization in Genome Assemblies. G3 9(10): 3101-3104

R. D. Perkins, J.R. Gamboa, **M.M. Jonika**, J. Lo, A. Shum, R.H. Adams, H. Blackmon. 2019. A Database of Amphibian Karyotypes. Chromosome Research 27: 313-319.

B. Guard, J Honneffer, A Jergens, **M.M. Jonika**, L. Toresson, Y. Lawrence, C. Webb, S. Hill, J. Lidbury, J. Steiner, J. Suchodolski. 2018. Longitudinal Assessment of Microbial Dysbiosis and Fecal Bile Acids Concentrations in Dogs with Chronic Inflammatory Enteropathy. J. of Vet. Internal Med. 33:1295-1305.